Margaret Widdemer Papers
Margaret Widdemer Papers
1923-1963
Widdemer, Margaret.
7.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, novelist, poet. Appointment books (1923-1962); manuscript poems and novels; articles, clippings, reviews, and scrapbooks.
148755
Biographical History
Margaret Widdemer (1884-1978) was an American author, novelist and poet.
Born in Doylestown, Pennsylvania, Ms. Widdemer attended Drexel, Bucknell, and Middlebury College. She began writing as a child and by 1916 had received the Trimmed Lamp prize for the best lyric. That same year she shared the American Poetry Society Pulitzer prize with Carl Sandburg. Her career as an author and poet continued, and she began to write essays, reviews, and short stories which were published in American magazines. Widdemer served as vice-president of the Poetry Society of America, and wrote several popular books, including Lady of the Mohawks, The Basic Techniques of Fiction, and Collected Poems. As an author she lectured widely and spoke on NBC radio in a series of talks titled "Do you Want To Write?" She spent most of her life in New York City.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Margaret Widdemer Papers consists of subject files, poems, poems set to music, manuscripts, microfilm, notes, published materials, clippings and scrapbooks.
All correspondence was returned to the donor in 1965, therefore Correspondence-subject files contains only subject files; these include appointment books, book reviews, royalty statements, some poems written by Ms. Widdemer's students, and assorted biographical and other material.
Poems contains more than fifty poems by Widdemer, while Poems set to music contains twenty or so of her poems that have set to music by various composers. In some cases, there are several different musical versions of a single poem.
Manuscripts contains those of novels and poems as well as an incomplete autobiography. This is followed by one reel of Microfilm (negative), containing "The Old Road to Paradise," and a small collection of Notes, both research and miscellaneous.
Published materials consists of published version of Widdemer's poems in a variety of publications, including Women's Day, Voices, Wisconsin Poetry Magazine, and The Lyric. Clippings include book reviews, articles, poetry, and other items.
Eighteen Scrapbooks (clippings, poems, recipes, and one on telepathy) complete the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
The series are in no particular order, but within each series material is arranged alphabetically by subject, type or title, as appropriate.
Related Material
See also the papers of her sister-in-law,
Mabel Cleland Widdemer
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Women Authors; Widdemer, Margaret.; American literature -- 20th century.; American poetry -- Women authors.; Women authors, American.; Women novelists, American.; Women poets, American.; Appointment books.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Manuscripts for publication.; Poems.; Reviews (documents); Scrapbooks.; Authors.; Novelists.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Folder "Poems, articles and proofs" in Box 6 marked on original finding aid as restricted (reason unknown). Thorough investigation turned up no documentation on this and Ms. Widdemer has been deceased for more than thirty years, therefore restriction lifted 3/4/09 (Michele Combs).
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Correspondence, All correspondence returned to donor, 1965
  - Appointment calendars
    - 1923-1930, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - 1931-1942, 12 folders (Box 2)
    - 1945-1962, 13 folders (Box 3)
  - Book reviews
    - The Dark Cavalier (Box 4)
    - The Golden Wildcat (Box 4)
    - The Graven Image (Box 4)
  - Lincoln pennies (Box 4)
  - Royalty statements, 1957; 1959 (Box 4)
  - Student poems to Margaret Widdemer (Box 4)
  - Widdemer, Margaret
    - Autobiographical and biographical (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Poems
  - Advice to a Poem (Box 4)
  - Alcaeus' Shell (Box 4)
  - Am I a Billiken (Box 4)
  - The Angel (Box 4)
  - Any Woman (Box 4)
  - Arabian Nights' Tale (Box 4)
  - Archetype (Box 4)
  - Ball Game (Box 4)
  - A Ballad of Drunken Honesty (Box 4)
  - Ballade of Discreet Ladies (Box 4)
  - Books (Box 4)
  - Barter Folder (Box 4)
  - Born Thus (Box 4)
  - Bright Journey Folder (Box 4)
  - Bugle (Box 4)
  - A Carol of Homecoming (Box 4)
  - Change of Lights (Box 4)
  - The Clever Ones (Box 4)
  - Convent Burial (Box 4)
  - Conversation of Skeletons (Box 4)
  - The Conquered Elm (Box 4)
  - The Costumer (Box 4)
  - Cycles (Box 4)
  - Dawn-Ship (Box 4)
  - Decoration: Driftwood (Box 4)
  - Delicious Landscape (Box 4)
  - Delta Night (Box 4)
  - Departure (Box 4)
  - Deus et Gladius (Box 4)
  - Diary for Bereavement (Box 4)
  - Exit (Box 4)
  - Fellow Traveler (Box 4)
  - Flight-1959 (Box 4)
  - The Flower of Sound (Box 4)
  - For the New Year (Box 4)
  - For an Old Clock with Roman Numerals (Box 4)
  - For Lack of Stars (Box 4)
  - For a Young Japanese Artist (Box 4)
  - Forward to Great Ladies (Box 4)
  - Forward to The Other Place (Box 4)
  - Forward to Queens (Box 4)
  - Funerals, Black and White (Box 4)
  - God and the Strong Ones (Box 4)
  - Grace During Living (Box 4)
  - Happiness is not a Ring (Box 4)
  - I Have Been Birds Here (Box 4)
  - Helen's Heart (Box 4)
  - A House by a River (Box 4)
  - Hurricane (Box 4)
  - It's a Living (Box 4)
  - The Jade Carver (Box 4)
  - Janua Vitae (Box 4)
  - Journey (Box 4)
  - Journey Toward Light (Box 4)
  - The Knights Return (Box 4)
  - Land's End (Box 4)
  - A Letter was Received (Box 4)
  - Light (Box 4)
  - Little Roads (Box 4)
  - The Lost People (Box 4)
  - Lullaby of the Bomb (Box 4)
  - Lullaby for Loneliness (Box 4)
  - Manet (Box 4)
  - Matilda's Woolwork (Box 4)
  - Mention My Name (Box 4)
  - Miyeko (Box 4)
  - Mirage (Box 4)
  - Modern Hymn for Grief (Box 4)
  - More Sinned Against Than Sinning (Box 4)
  - The Mourner (Box 4)
  - Night Before Harvest (Box 4)
  - The Not-Quite Spring (Box 4)
  - Old Books (Box 4)
  - Old Ladies (Box 4)
  - Old Music (Box 4)
  - Older Women (Box 4)
  - On the Sweat of the Toilers (Box 4)
  - On Walking (Box 4)
  - Once Upon a Time a Cow (Box 4)
  - Only the Word Survives (Box 4)
  - Orange Birds (Box 4)
  - Petition (Box 4)
  - The Place (Box 4)
  - The Pleasure of Waiting (Box 4)
  - Plurale Tantum (Box 4)
  - Poem for a Gravestone (Box 4)
  - A Poem Is Less Than A Child (Box 4)
  - Poems by Margaret, written when a young girl (Box 4)
  - Portrait Framed in Driftwood (Box 4)
  - Return (Box 4)
  - Return (Box 4)
  - Revisitants (Box 4)
  - The Road to Downderry (Box 4)
  - Romantic (Box 4)
  - Romantique (Box 4)
  - Round (Box 4)
  - Search (Box 4)
  - Search (Box 4)
  - Seaside Summer (Box 4)
  - Sea Story (Box 4)
  - Shell (Box 4)
  - Sired by Old Singers (Box 4)
  - Snow at Night (Box 4)
  - Some Erring Ladies Explain (Box 4)
  - Some was Reality (Box 4)
  - Song: I wish I were old now (Box 4)
  - Song of a Swimmer (Box 4)
  - Song Without Words (Box 4)
  - Spanish Ladies (Box 4)
  - Spring Moment (Box 4)
  - Stars (Box 4)
  - Stopover: Frankfurt (Box 4)
  - The Sun Will Rise Once More (Box 4)
  - Survivor (Box 4)
  - Tally Card (Box 4)
  - Thou art That (Box 4)
  - To Sleep, Perchance (Box 4)
  - To Stones From a New England Beach-An Ode (Box 4)
  - A Thought, Perhaps (Box 4)
  - Toward the Light (Box 4)
  - Triumph (Box 4)
  - Untitled (Box 4)
  - Vivien's Lesson (Box 4)
  - The Voice of Youth (Box 4)
  - Warning (Box 4)
  - The Well (Box 4)
  - White Bird Flying (Box 4)
  - Wisdom (Box 4)
  - With Aching Wooden Heart (Box 4)
  - Words for Blowing of the Ram's Horn (Box 4)
  - World's End (Box 4)
  - The Worthiest Go Down (Box 4)
  - The World I Walk In (Box 4)
  - Your Love Will Live (Box 4)
- Poems set to music
  - After, music by Ann Gardner (Box 5)
  - After, music by Homer Grunn (Box 5)
  - Ballad of St. John (Cathile) (Box 5)
  - A Carol of the Star, music by Caroline Dietz (Box 5)
  - Changed, music by Harry A. Anik (Box 5)
  - A Cyprian Woman, music by Mildred T. Ross (Box 5)
  - The Dark Cavalier, Music by S. W. Dotz (Box 5)
  - The Dark Cavalier, music by M. Wood-Hill (Box 5)
  - The Dark Cavalier, music by Florance H. (?) (Box 5)
  - Every Town's Your Home Town, music by Gena Branscombe (Box 5)
  - If You Should Tire of Loving Me, music by Louis Drakeford (Box 5)
  - If You Should Tire of Loving Me, music by Edward Mack (Box 5)
  - Jester's Bells, music by Homer Grunn (Box 5)
  - John of the Wanderings, music by Margaret Widdemer (Box 5)
  - Little Roads, music by Louise H. Snodgrass (Box 5)
  - Lord, Gods We Lift to Thee, music by Clarence Dickinson (Box 5)
  - Marching Feet, music by Martha Cook Hulett (Box 5)
  - Mary, Helper of Heart Break, music by Harold Barrett, Jr. (Box 5)
  - Mother, music by Richard Hageman (Box 5)
  - A New Spinning Song, music by Louis Drakeford (Box 5)
  - The Old Gods Dream (Box 5)
  - Organ Music in the Rain, music by Charles W. Cadman (Box 5)
  - The Quest Eternal, music by Clarence Dickinson (Box 5)
  - Roses Breathe into the Night, music by Marion Bauer (Box 5)
  - Singing Wood (Box 5)
  - Swanhild's Song (What Shall I Do with My Heart) (Box 5)
  - Unsung Hour, music by Cyril de Brant (Box 5)
  - Where Go Ye, music by Hugh A. Mac Kinnon (Box 5)
  - The Willow-Cats, music by Sandor Harmati (Box 5)
  - The Watcher, music by Louis Nicholas (Box 5)
  - The Watcher, music by Edna Randolph Worrell (Box 5)
  - The Watchers, music by Edward Shippen Barnes (Box 5)
  - The Watchers, music by Henrietta E. Enners (Box 5)
  - Untitled (My heart is very quiet now), music by Lois Mosby (Box 5)
  - Breast the Wave, music and words by Rev. E. S. Widdemer (Box 5)
- Manuscripts
  - Autobiography, incomplete (Box 5)
  - Buckskin Baronet, novel, chapts. 1-21; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - The Dark Cavalier, Collected poems, pp. 1-283; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Golden Friends I Had, galley proof (Box 5)
  - Lady of the Mohawks, incomplete, typescript carbon (Box 6A)
  - MacDowell Colony, galley proofs (Box 6A)
  - My Mother Used Cliches, incomplete (missing as of 3/9/09)
  - Poems, articles, and proofs (Box 6A)
  - The Soft Touch, incomplete (Box 6A)
  - Strange Woman's Son, incomplete, original manuscript (Box 6A)
  - Untitled, also Sonnet For a Buried Season, 33 pages (Box 6A)
- Microfilm
  - "The Old Road to Paradise", negative; 1 reel (Cabinet 5, Drawer 1)
- Notes
  - Fort Ontario Indian Research, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Reasons for the Revolutionary War (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (found with music of Margaret Widdemer) (Box 7)
- Published Materials
  - "As I Lay Quiet" (Box 7)
  - "The Baby Liked 'Greensleeves" Plays, December, 1943 (Box 7)
  - "A Ballad of Queen Elizabeth" Voices, September-December, 1951 (Box 7)
  - "Blessing" (Box 7)
  - "Bright Journey" Christian Herald, 1957 (Box 7)
  - "City Spring","Light Heart", "Heaven" Wisconsin Poetry Magazine, November-December, 1958 (Box 7)
  - "Do You Secretly Fear Love?" Your Life, December, 1943 (Box 7)
  - "Forbidden", "Promise" Wisconsin Poetry Magazine, March-April, 1959 (Box 7)
  - "Four Women Lyricists" (Box 7)
  - "The Great Ships Come" (Box 7)
  - "Heaven" (Box 7)
  - "How To's for Happiness" Woman's Day, June, 1959 (Box 7)
  - "I'm a Bonga Woman" Woman's Day, 1956 (Box 7)
  - "Judith's Father" Plays, April, 1944 (Box 7)
  - "The Man Says Yes" Liberty Magazine, 1939 (Box 7)
  - "No Master Dog" Classmate, vol. L, no. 37, September, 1943 (Box 7)
  - "Old House" Wisconsin Poetry Magazine, November-December, 1958 (Box 7)
  - "Old Village" Wisconsin Poetry Magazine, January-February, 1959 (Box 7)
  - "Paragraph" Five Modern Poems, Kane, 1936 (Box 7)
  - "Picnic" Classmate vol. L, no. 23, June 1963 (Box 7)
  - "Prince in Buckskin" American Heritage (Box 7)
  - "Return" The Poesy Book, vol. 1, no. 3, Winter, 1942-1943 (Box 7)
  - "St. Martin's Summer" Voices, 1957 (Box 7)
  - "So I Sent My True Love" Pictorial Review (Box 7)
  - "Song" The Lyric Winter, 1959 (Box 7)
  - "To an Old Day" Wings, 1957 (Box 7)
  - "Youth Laughs" (Box 7)
- Clippings
  - Biography and engagements (Box 8)
  - Book reviews (Box 8)
  - Book reviews, miscellaneous, short articles (Box 8)
  - Poetry and biography (Box 8)
  - Reviews, poems, biography (Box 8)
  - Teaching (Box 8)
- Scrapbooks
  - Biographical (Box 9)
  - Clippings
    - Poems, biographical (Box 9)
    - Biographical, poems (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Poetry
    - Poetry scrapbook no. 1 (Box 11)
    - Poetry scrapbook no. 2 (Box 11)
    - Poetry scrapbook no. 3 (Box 11)
    - Poetry scrapbook no. 4 (Box 11)
    - Poetry scrapbook no. 5 (Box 11)
    - Poetry scrapbook no. 6 (Box 11)
    - Poetry scrapbook no. 7 (Box 12)
  - Published material
    - [Untitled] (Box 12)
    - No. 2, November, 1914-March, 1918 (Oversize 1)
    - No. 3, October, 1918-November, 1923 (Oversize 2)
    - No. 4, 1923-1929 (Oversize 1)
  - Recipes (Box 13)
  - Scraps (Box 13)
  - Telepathy (Box 13)